My book How Not To Age,
is all about the mechanisms of aging
and how we can affect them
through diet and lifestyle.
Can looking at epigenetics,
modifiers of gene expression
help predict
our health span and lifespan?
Watch to find out.
"Epigenetic Clocks
for Testing Your Biological Age"
Epigenetics-the differential
expression of genes-
both establishes the character
and function of a cell
and maintains that identity
over time
through round after round
of cell division.
So, a heart cell
stays a heart cell
and divides
to make more heart cells,
instead of skin cells
or kidney cells,
even though all our main cells
have the same
entire complement of DNA
to potentially be anything.
This is accomplished
by methylation,
chemical markers that silence
inappropriate genes
in a particular cell.
The fidelity
of that maintenance
of methylation is good-
97 percent to 99.9 percent
every division-but not perfect.
Over time, those tiny errors
may add up
and may help explain why
the methylation patterns
of identical twins
drift apart as they age.
The epigenetic markers
of young identical twins
are essentially
indistinguishable
but then diverge over time.
Identical twins have
the same DNA, the same genes,
but the difference
in gene expression
among older
identical twin pairs
were found to be
about four times greater
than those observed
in young pairs.
This may result in them each
getting different diseases.
An age-related disease
like Alzheimer's
only has an identical twin
concordance rate
of about 50 percent,
meaning if one twin gets it,
there's only
about a coin flip chance
that the other will too,
despite identical DNA.
Or, even if they do
both get it,
the disease may manifest
decades apart.
Any epigenetic differences
that may contribute
to differential disease rates
may arise from having
different diets and lifestyles
or may be a result
of random epigenetic drift.
However, there are
certain DNA sites
on our chromosomes
that predictably methylate
or demethylate as we age.
So predictable, in fact,
it's like clockwork.
One of the earliest attempts
to study aging
and the epigenome
(which is only
like a dozen years ago)
found that the DNA
from a 103-year-old
appeared to be
less methylated overall
than the DNA
of a newborn infant,
suggesting, perhaps,
that aging involves
the general loss
of epigenetic markings.
We now know
it's more complicated than that.
Of the methylation sites
that reliably change as we age,
about 60 percent go
from methylated to unmethylated,
and the other 40 percent become
more methylated over time.
Some so reliably change
with age
that they've been considered
a "molecular crystal ball
for human aging."
In a remarkable triumph
of Big Data,
out of the millions
of methylation sites
in our DNA,
a tiny subset
so dependably shift over time
that you can predict
someone's age
within a few years
just by strategically measuring
the methylation pattern
in a few hundred
or even just a few dozen sites
in someone's
three-billion-letter genome.
Over just the last few years,
these "epigenetic clocks"
have become established
as robust measures
of chronological age,
surpassing telomere length
as the best age predictor.
Who cares, though?
I mean, why invent some costly
Rube Goldberg approach
to divining someone's age
when you can simply ask them?
Well, you can imagine
forensic applications,
the determination
of an unidentified victim's age
with a blood sample,
but that's just scratching
the surface.
The kicker is
that epigenetic clocks
don't just track
your chronological age
but appear to measure
your true biological age.
In other words,
your epigenetic age
can better predict
your remaining life expectancy
than your calendar age.
It's like science fiction.
Feed a drop of blood
into some futuristic machine
that scans the placement
of chemical markers
on a strand of DNA,
and it spits out your true age,
reflecting a lifetime
of lifestyle choices.
If the machine calculated
that you have
the DNA methylation pattern
of a 60-year-old, but you've
only had 50 birthdays,
that would be an example of
"epigenetic age acceleration,"
when your epigenetic clock age
is older
than your actual
chronological age.
That would be an indication
that you're aging too fast.
As a 50-year-old,
you'd think you have another,
mm, 30 years on this Earth,
but because
the epigenetic clock shows
that you're aging
at such an accelerated pace,
it's more like you only have
another 20 years left.
Every five years
of epigenetic age acceleration
is associated
with an 8 to 15 percent
increased risk of mortality.
In addition to predicting
time-to-death,
epigenetic clocks
also appear to foretell
healthspan indicators,
such as cognitive decline,
frailty, arthritis,
and the progression of diseases
like Alzheimer's
and Parkinson's.
As you can imagine,
the insurance agency*
has jumped on this,
and your premiums
may soon be determined
by your epigenetic age.
But it's not some
Gypsy fortune teller curse
set in stone.
You can change the rate
at which you age
and may soon be able
to use epigenetic clocks
to track your progress,
potentially presenting
a radically faster
and cheaper way to test
anti-aging interventions.